Guide to the Difference, Power, and Discrimination Program Records 1970-2011
Oregon State University Libraries, Special Collections and Archives Research Center
Difference, Power, and Discrimination Program Records
1970-2011
1991-2005
Oregon State University. Difference, Power and Discrimination Program.
RG 250
4.00 cubic feet, including 106 audiocassettes, 2 videotapes, and 2 DVDs; 29.5 Mbytes (494 files) 9 boxes, including 1 oversize box
29.5 Mbytes 494 files
Special Collections and Archives Research Center 121 The Valley Library Oregon State University Corvallis, OR, 97331-4501 Phone: 541-737-2075 Email: scarc@oregonstate.edu Web: http://scarc.library.oregonstate.edu/findingaids
The Difference, Power, and Discrimination (DPD) Program Records document the establishment and functioning of the DPD Program at Oregon State University as well as the topics of diversity, discrimination, racism, minority students and faculty, and women in higher education. The DPD Program at Oregon State University was established in the early 1990s as a means to deliver courses to address cultural and ethnic diversity as well as racism, discrimination, and their origins. Access to the transcripts and notes for interview with no releases in Series 7, Sub-Series 3 is restricted. All requests for access to this material should be directed to the University Archivist.
Historical Note:
The Difference, Power, and Discrimination (DPD) Program at Oregon State University was established in the early 1990s as a means to deliver courses to address cultural and ethnic diversity as well as racism, discrimination, and their origins. The initiating action for the DPD Program was a November 1990 letter from concerned student leaders to OSU President John Byrne proposing several actions in response to recent incidents of discrimination and harassment at OSU. One of these proposals was the development of mandatory courses for all students. In the Spring of 1992, the Faculty Senate approved the incorporation of the Difference, Power, and Discrimination requirement into the Baccalaureate Core, contingent on the development of enough courses. The DPD Program was created to provide faculty with the training and resources to develop or modify courses to meet the DPD criteria; the intent was that courses would address issues of diversity and discrimination not only in society in general, but within specific academic disciplines. Annie Popkin was chosen as the first director in June 1992. By Fall 1994, within two years of its establishment, a sufficient number of DPD courses were in place for the DPD requirement to become a component of the Baccalaureate Core. A comprehensive assessment and evaluation of the Program was conducted in 1998.
In addition to faculty seminars, the DPD Program sponsors guest speakers, film festivals, informal workshops and seminars, and other special events.
The following individuals have served as Director of the DPD Program since its establishment: Annie Popkin (1994), Barbara Paige (1994-1996), Mina Carson (1996-1997), Joan Gross (1998-1999); Susan Shaw (1999-2002), Jun Xing (2002-2011), Michelle Bothwell (2011-2014), and Nana Osi-Kofi (2014- ).
Carson, Mina Julia.; Gross, Joan.; Shaw, Susan M. (Susan Maxine), 1960-; Xing, Jun.
Oregon State University--Curricula.; Oregon State University. Difference, Power and Discrimination Program.
Audiocassettes.; Born digital.; DVDs.; Video recordings.
Minority college students--Oregon--Corvallis.; Minority college students--Recruiting--Oregon.; Minority college teachers--Oregon--Corvallis.; Multicultural education--Oregon.; Women--Education (Higher)--Oregon--Corvallis.
Colleges and Universities; Multiculturalism; Women; Oregon; Corvallis; Electronic Records; Moving Images; Oral Histories; Sound Recordings
The bulk of the materials were transferred from the Difference, Power, and Discrimination (DPD) Program in 2015. A small quantity of materials were transferred from Student Affairs in 2012 and incorporated into this collection in 2018.
Access to the transcripts and notes for interview with no releases in Series 7, Sub-Series 3 is restricted. All requests for access to this material should be directed to the University Archivist. All other materials in this collection are open for research.
The Difference, Power, and Discrimination (DPD) Program Records are a component of the Oregon Multicultural Archives, which includes numerous collections that document diversity and multicultural programs at Oregon State University. Other collections pertaining to multicultural education are the records of Affirmative Action (RG 172), the Office of Multicultural Affairs (RG 225), the President’s Commission on the Status of Women (RG 159), and the Women’s Center (RG 243). The Jean Moule Papers (MSS Moule) document multicultural education in the context of teacher training.
The Difference, Power, and Discrimination (DPD) Program Records are arranged in 11 series: 1. Correspondence, 1991-2007; 2. Course Proposals, 1991-2005; 3. Faculty Seminar, 1992-2011; 4. Reports, 1994-2004; 5. Reference Materials, 1970-2007; 6. Committee Records, 1991-2005; 7. Oral History Interviews, 1998; 8. Program Administration, 1991-2005; 9. Publications, 1994-2006; 10. Video and Sound Recordings, 1987-2008; and 11. Born-Digital Materials, 1997-1998.
The Difference, Power, and Discrimination (DPD) Program Records document the establishment and functioning of the DPD Program at Oregon State University as well as the topics of diversity, discrimination, racism, minority students and faculty, and women in higher education. The records pertain to curriculum development and pedagogy at Oregon State University specific to diversity and multicultural education as well as undergraduate education generally in all academic disciplines.
The records include materials documenting program administration, course proposals, committees, and the annual faculty seminar. Reports that are specific to the DPD Program and pertain to broader issues of diversity and equity at Oregon State are included. Reference materials that were assembled by the DPD Program as resources and reference materials for administration, teaching, and course development are part of the collection. These materials document specific incidents, racism, diversity and discrimination, recruitment and retention of minority faculty and students, and the role of women and minorities in science.
A 1998 review and evaluation of the DPD Program is comprehensively documented in the collection – especially a series of oral history interviews conducted by students in an anthropology class of other Oregon State students regarding DPD courses.
The collection also includes promotional publications, the Program's newsletter ReVisions, and several audio and video recordings. Video recordings of lectures by Nikki Giovanni and Gloria Anzaldua are available online.
Born-digital records are available to researchers in the Special Collections and Archives Research Center Reading Room.
- Correspondence, 1991-2007; Series 1
  Series 1 consists of correspondence received and sent by the DPD Program director and affiliated faculty, including Lani Roberts, Susan Shaw, Joan Gross, and Barbara Paige. Much of the correspondence is printed e-mail messages. The correspondence pertains to program administration, including budgets; workshops and publications; and DPD courses. This series includes born digital materials (4 files; 23 kbytes) that are available to researchers in the Reading Room.
  - Joan Gross, 1991-2000 (Box-folder 1.01)
  - E-mails, 1992-2007 (Box-folder 1.02)
  - Budgets, 1992-2001 (Box-folder 1.03)
  - General, 1993-2004 (Box-folder 1.04)
  - Essay Contest, 1994 (Box-folder 1.05)
  - Workshops, 1995-2001 (Box-folder 1.06)
  - Baccalaureate Core Course Review, 1996-2004 (Box-folder 1.07)
  - Response to Proposed Elimination of DPD, 1998 (Box-folder 1.08)
  - Susan Shaw, 1999-2001 (Box-folder 1.09)
  - Seminar for Graduate Students, 2001 (Box-folder 1.10)
  - Book Publication: Teaching DPD at OSU, 2005-2006 (Box-folder 1.11)
  - Correspondence, 1994-1997 (Box-folder 3.47)
  - Letters, 1995
    Correspondence from DPD Director Barbara Paige regarding textbooks, course proposals, and other administrative matters. This folder includes 4 files (all Word documents) totaling 23 kbytes.
- Course Proposals, 1991-2005; Series 2
  Series 2 consists of course proposals and associated documentation submitted to the Baccalaureate Core Committee. The proposals address how courses meet the criteria established by the Faculty Senate for DPD courses within the Baccalaureate Core curriculum. Lists of DPD courses, syllabi, and review materials are included in this series. This series includes born digital materials (4 files; 33 kbytes) that are available to researchers in the Reading Room.
  - Course Lists, Syllabi, and Proposals, 1991-2004 (Box-folder 1.12)
  - Course Proposals, 1993-1995 (Box-folder 1.13)
  - Course Proposals, 1993-1997 (Box-folder 1.14)
  - Course Proposals, 1994-1997 (Box-folder 1.15)
  - Course Proposals, 1994-1999 (Box-folder 1.16)
  - Course Proposals, 2002-2004 (Box-folder 1.17)
  - Baccalaureate Core Review Syllabi, 2004-2005 (Box-folder 1.18)
  - Correspondence and Proposal, 1996
    Correspondence pertaining to the approval of DPD courses and a proposal for HST 368X. These born digital materials (4 files; 33 kbytes) are available to researchers in the Reading Room.
- Faculty Seminar, 1992-2011; Series 3
  Series 3 consists of records of the faculty seminar offered annually in the summer as an intensive 3-week seminar. The purpose of the seminar is to help faculty transform their curricula in light of issues of difference, power, and discrimination. This series includes outlines for the seminar, readings, applications from faculty to participate in the seminar, and evaluations. Materials documenting a seminar for Graduate Teaching Assistants (GTA) in September 2001 are also included. The series includes born digital materials (61 files; 1.8 Mbytes) that are available to researchers in the Reading Room.
  - Applications and Agreements, 1992-1993 (Box-folder 1.19)
  - Applications and Agreements, 1994-1995 (Box-folder 1.20)
  - Applications and Agreements, 1996-1997 (Box-folder 1.21)
  - Applications and Agreements, 2003-2009 (Box-folder 1.22)
  - Evaluation Questionnaires, 1992-1993 (Box-folder 1.23)
  - Evaluation Questionnaires, 1994-1999 (Box-folder 1.24)
  - Evaluation Questionnaires- Raw E-mails, 1998 (Box-folder 1.25)
  - Evaluation Questionnaires, 2003-2007 (Box-folder 1.26)
  - Ideas from 1992, 1993, and 1997 Faculty Seminars, 1992-1997 (Box-folder 2.01)
  - Faculty Seminar Outlines and Reading, 1992-2009 (Box-folder 2.02)
    Includes Linn-Benton Seminar
  - 2011 Summer Faculty Seminar (Box-folder 2.03)
  - Faculty Seminar, 1993-2002
    Correspondence, publicity, evaluation, and resources documenting seminars and training offered to faculty for developing DPD courses. These born-digital records (56 files; 1.5 Mbytes) consist primarily of Word documents and also include Microsoft Publisher files, and Excel spreadsheets. The records are available to researchers in the Reading Room.
  - GTA Seminar, 2001
    Materials documenting a seminar of graduate teaching assistants offered in September. These born-digital records (5 files; 335 kbytes) are primarily Word documents and one Publisher file. The materials are available to researchers in the Reading Room.
- Reports, 1994-2004; Series 4
  Series 4 consists of reports prepared or received by the DPD Program and includes DPD annual reports for 1993-1994, 1996-1997, and 1998. The 1999 report of the assessment of the DPD program that was conducted in 1998 is also part of this series. The assessment report includes copies of initiating and founding documents for the Program as appendices. Reports pertaining to recruitment, retention, equity, and parity for women and minority faculty are also part of this series. Born digital materials (3 files; 26 kbytes) are available for researchers in the Reading Room.
  - DPD Program: A Four Year Development Plan, 1994 (Box-folder 2.04)
  - Status of Minority Faculty Recruitment and Retention, 1994 (Box-folder 2.05)
  - Interim Report for Reaffirmation of Accreditation, 1995 (Box-folder 2.06)
  - DPD Annual Report, 1996-1997 (Box-folder 2.07)
  - Draft Assessment of the DPD Program, 1999 (Box-folder 2.08)
  - Final Assessment of the DPD Program, 1999 (Box-folder 2.09)
  - DPD Task Force Report to the Faculty Senate, 2000 (Box-folder 2.1)
  - Report to OSU Student Affairs Department Heads from the Diversity Programs Work Group, 2001 (Box-folder 2.11)
  - Inter-Institutional Faculty Senate and Transfer Model, 2004 (Box-folder 2.12)
  - The Path to Parity for Women at OSU, 2004 (Box-folder 2.13)
  - Annual Reports, 1994-1998
    Annual reports of the DPD Program for 1993-1994 and 1998 and correspondence pertaining to the 1998 report. These born-digital materials (3 files; 26 kbytes) consist of 2 Word Perfect files and one Word document. The materials are available to researchers in the Reading Room.
- Reference Materials, 1970-2007; Series 5
  Series 5 consists of materials assembled by the DPD Program as resources and reference materials for administration, teaching, and course development. The materials include reports, published articles, planning documents for other OSU units, newspaper clippings, and related documentation and correspondence. The reference materials address a myriad of topics including diversity and discrimination, minority faculty and students, racism, women, and the role of women and minorities in science. The series includes born-digital materials (7 files; 7.7 Mbytes) that are available to researchers in the Reading Room.
  - OSU: Status of Women, Equal Employment, HEW, and Women's Study Group (folder 1/2), 1970-1978 (Box-folder 2.14)
    HEW: Department of Health, Education, and Welfare
  - OSU: Status of Women, Equal Employment, HEW, and Women's Study Group (folder 2/2), 1970-1978 (Box-folder 2.15)
  - University of Oregon: Women in Sciences and Multicultural Debates, 1985-1994 (Box-folder 2.16)
  - Feminism and Science, 1986 (Box-folder 2.17)
  - Teaching Equality Articles and Controversial News, 1987-2003 (Box-folder 2.18)
  - History of Discrimination: Oregon and Diversity Development Plan, 1987-2009 (Box-folder 2.19)
  - Reference Materials, circa 1988 (Box-folder 2.20)
  - "Minorities, Discrimination, and Change at OSU", 1988-1993 (Box-folder 2.21)
  - Racism at OSU, 1988-2004 (Box-folder 2.22)
  - Spring Seminar: Unmasking the Myths of Racism, 1989-1992 (Box-folder 2.23)
  - Science, 1990-2001 (Box-folder 2.24)
    General references.
  - "Racism at OSU", 1991-1993 (Box-folder 2.25)
  - Science and Women and Scientific Illiteracy, 1991-1993 (Box-folder 2.26)
  - Teaching Diversity Articles, 1991-1996 (Box-folder 2.27)
  - C. Kreiner "Interview on Oppression", 1992 (Box-folder 2.28)
  - Incidents at OSU: Civil War T-shirt, and Playboy, 1993 (Box-folder 2.29)
  - OSU Women's Issues, 1993-1999 (Box-folder 2.30)
  - OSU Minority Science Program, 1994 (Box-folder 2.31)
  - Press Release Packets, 1994 (Box-folder 2.32)
  - "The First Oregonians" and Native American Longhouse, 1994 (Box-folder 2.33)
  - Recruitment and Retention Materials, 1994-1995 (Box-folder 2.34)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1994-2000 (Box-folder 2.35)
  - Students and Faculty of Color: Information, 1995-1996 (Box-folder 2.36)
  - History of Science, 1997-2002 (Box-folder 2.37)
  - ASOSU Recommends No Confidence Vote for President-Elect, 1998 (Box-folder 2.38)
  - Defining "Science" in a Multicultural World, 1998 (Box-folder 2.39)
  - Writing for Change, 2000 (Box-folder 2.40)
  - Technology Dealing with Gender, 2001 (Box-folder 2.41)
  - Diverse Faculty Arguments, 2002 (Box-folder 2.42)
  - Diversity Target Market Plan, circa 1997 (Box-folder 2.43)
    African American student recruitment.
  - Distinguished Lecturer, 2003 (Box-folder 2.44)
  - Feminist Perspectives, 2006 (Box-folder 2.45)
  - Academic Affairs International Programs (AAIP) Diversity Plan, 2005-2007 (Box-folder 2.46)
  - Articles, circa 2007 (Box-folder 2.47)
  - Comic Strips and Discussion Posters, circa 1990s (Box-folder 2.48)
  - Clippings, Articles, and Publications, 1993-1999 (Box-folder 2.49)
  - Report - Achieving Parity for Women at OSU, 1994 (Box-folder 2.50)
  - Shoemaker Oregon, 2007
    Agenda and presentation for the Oregon State Service-Learning Faculty Seminar on May 11, 2007, "Developing a Scholarship of Engagement and Social Justice", presented by Jan Shoemaker, Director of the Louisiana State University Center for Community Engagement, Learning, and Leadership. These born digital materials (7 files; 7.7 Mbytes) consist of one Word document and 6 Powerpoint files. The materials are available for researchers in the Reading Room.
- Committee Records, 1991-2005; Series 6
  Series 6 consists of the records of the Difference, Power, and Discrimination Program Advisory Board; the Faculty Senate Difference, Power, and Discrimination Task Force; and other Oregon State University committees and councils pertaining to diversity. Records of a committee to develop courses affirming diversity, that precedes the formal establishment of the DPD Program, are also part of this series. The materials in this series include minutes, agendas, meeting notes, and related documentation and correspondence.
  - Affirming Diversity Course Development Committee, 1991-1992 (Box-folder 3.01)
  - Diversity Action Coalition, 1993 (Box-folder 3.02)
  - Meeting Minutes, 1993-2005 (Box-folder 3.03)
  - Difference, Power, and Discrimination OSU Program- Department Support, 1994-1995 (Box-folder 3.04)
  - Difference, Power, and Discrimination Program Advisory Board, 1994-2005 (Box-folder 3.05)
  - Faculty Senate Difference, Power, and Discrimination Task Force, 1999-2000 (Box-folder 3.06)
  - Baccalaureate Core Committee Assessment, 1999-2005 (Box-folder 3.07)
  - Diversity Council / Committee, 2001 (Box-folder 3.08)
  - Goals and Aspect Map, 2004-2005 (Box-folder 3.09)
  - Meeting Notes, 2004-2005 (Box-folder 3.10)
- Oral History Interviews, 1998; Series 7
  Series 7 consists of sound recordings and transcripts of interviews conducted as a review and assessment of the DPD Program in 1998.This series consists of 3 sub-series: 1. Sound Recordings; 2. Releases, Transcripts, and Notes; and 3. Transcripts and Notes for Interviews without Releases. The materials within each sub-series are arranged by the interviewer.
  The interviews were conducted by students in Joan Gross' Oral Traditions course (ANTH 498/598) during fall term of 1998; the interviewees were other Oregon State University students who had completed a DPD course. The semi-structured interviews gathered information about students' perception of the goals of the DPD Program, their knowledge of diversity and discrimination issues before and after taking a DPD course, and their assessment of the course and the program overall.
  The sound recordings are cassette tapes and are available for listening in the Special Collections and Archives Research Center Reading Room.
  Transcripts and notes are available for many of the interviews. Transcripts and notes for interviews without releases are restricted. There are several sound recordings that include interviews with individuals for whom there are no releases; these are indicated in the list below.
  The data and conclusions reached from these interviews are summarized in the 1999 assessment report in Series 4.
  - Sound Recordings
    - Armelle Denis
      - Mary McClure tape 1/2 (Box-item 4.01)
      - Mary McClure tape 2/2 (Box-item 4.02)
      - Sarin Spehar, October 18th (Box-item 4.03)
      - Jennifer Shukri (Box-item 4.04)
      - Patty Sweat (Box-item 4.05)
      - Greg Less (Box-item 4.06)
      - Wendy Cronin (Box-item 4.07)
      - Jeanna Bush, November 13th (Box-item 4.08)
      - Monica Rojas, November 15th (Box-item 4.09)
      - Sarin Spehar, November 17th (Box-item 4.10)
      - Brian Wenzl (Box-item 4.11)
      - Monica Rojas, November 22nd (Box-item 4.12)
      - Nathan Bader (Box-item 4.13)
      - Jeanna Bush, November 25th (Box-item 4.14)
    - Becca Zimmer-Wolf
      - Cathleen Mosubrocki (Box-item 4.15)
        Includes Follow-up
      - Mandie Bewley (Box-item 4.16)
      - Silas Richardson (Box-item 4.17)
      - Andrew Biskey (Box-item 4.18)
      - Jamie Denton (Box-item 4.19)
      - Jay Kirby and Danny Saecho (Box-item 4.20)
      - John Steele (Box-item 4.21)
      - Jeff Campbell (Box-item 4.22)
    - David Baldassano
      - Susan Nall (Box-item 4.23)
      - Derek Ottele (Box-item 4.24)
      - James Rogers, October 21st and November 12th (Box-item 4.25)
      - Faron Anslow, October 23rd and November 16th (Box-item 4.26)
      - Jesse Putman (Box-item 4.27)
      - Angela Lau (Box-item 4.28)
      - James Udoka (Box-item 4.29)
      - Colleen Cordis (Box-item 4.30)
      - Maija Gunderson (Box-item 4.31)
      - Megan Kalstad (Box-item 4.32)
        Interviewed with an individual for whom there is no release.
    - Eben Haase
      - Daniel Olvera and Brittney Powell, October 16th and 26th (Box-item 4.33)
      - Jesse Downing and Jose Pizano (Box-item 4.34)
      - Renato Quintero and Jenny Semadeni, November 4th and 11th (Box-item 4.35)
      - Renato Quintero and T.J. Jeppesen, November 29th (Box-item 4.36)
      - Marisa Fernandez and Daniel Olvera, November 30th (Box-item 4.37)
      - Ramona Flores and Maria Villalobos (Box-item 4.38)
    - Heather Burns
      - Lisa N. (Box-item 5.01)
      - Nancy, October 16th (Box-item 5.02)
      - Angela Cordova (Box-item 5.03)
      - Michael Sugihara, October 22nd (Box-item 5.04)
      - William Andersen (Box-item 5.05)
      - Benn Eilers (Box-item 5.06)
      - Dan Auger (Box-item 5.07)
      - David Jackman and Tammi Jackman (Box-item 5.08)
      - Kristina Small (Box-item 5.09)
      - Nancy, November 19th (Box-item 5.10)
      - Michael Sugihara, November 23rd (Box-item 5.11)
    - Jennifer Leaver
      - Andre Moen and Machelle Nelson (Box-item 5.12)
      - Fred Kummernes and Dorothy Sandoval (Box-item 5.13)
      - Laura Baxter and Jaime Race (Box-item 5.14)
      - Kom-Dui So and Jeremy Baker (Box-item 5.15)
      - Ellie Larsen and Charlie Bisgord (Box-item 5.16)
      - Interview 1 and 2 (Box-item 5.17)
      - Interview 3 and 4 (Box-item 5.18)
    - Laura Henderson
      - Michael Edwards, October 18th (Box-item 5.19)
      - Ravi Puri and Karianne Stinson (Box-item 5.20)
      - Lisa Hobart (Box-item 5.21)
      - Justin Timmons (Box-item 5.22)
      - Melanie Spraggins (Box-item 5.23)
      - Suzanne Gaulocher (Box-item 5.24)
      - Jessica Leahy (Box-item 5.25)
      - Timothy Tedder (Box-item 5.26)
      - Kevin Pardew (Box-item 5.27)
      - Jill Brunell (Box-item 5.28)
      - Brenda Johnson (Box-item 5.29)
      - Michael Edwards, December 1st (Box-item 5.30)
    - Nicko Widjaja
      - Thomas Tu, Patrick, and Frans Marbun (Box-item 5.31)
      - Mutiara Moesaffa and Ceryl Susilo (Box-item 5.32)
        Includes interviews with individuals for whom there are no releases.
      - Jamie Toman, Khaled Abmussallam, Andrew Kim, and Sutrisno Amidjojo (Box-item 5.33)
    - Pei-Yao Lee
      - Chi-Yu Wang (Box-item 5.34)
        Includes interview with individual for whom there is no release.
      - Carl Erhardt (Box-item 5.35)
      - Michael Giles (Box-item 5.36)
      - Gregory Jones (Box-item 5.37)
      - Emily Schlumbohm (Box-item 5.38)
      - Takayuki Nishio (Box-item 5.39)
      - I-Ping Huang (Box-item 6.01)
      - Doug Holdt (Box-item 6.02)
      - Terry Wright (Box-item 6.03)
      - Minori Fukushima (Box-item 6.04)
    - Sheila Ford
      - Timothy Lang and Christian Bushong, October 20th and October 29th (Box-item 6.05)
      - Mary Martin and Terry Wright (Box-item 6.06)